You may have heard about this big study
that recently released that implicates
elemental lithium in preserving and even
reversing signs of devastating cognitive
condition Alzheimer's disease. Well, we
went over it here too, including the
clinical data in humans, but I'd like to
take you a layer deeper in understanding
exactly how lithium is proposed to
defend our brain cells against
Alzheimer's disease. because there's a
few different ways and they largely
hinge on one devious enzyme, GSK3.
The thing is, lithium, a mineral, can
correct a major problem in Alzheimer's
disease called long-term potentiation,
LTP as the cool kids call it, is in very
simple terms, the capacity for your
neurons, your brain cells to strengthen
their connections with one another. This
is a key consequence of Alzheimer's
disease. Reduced LTP. Now, this
mischievous enzyme GSK3 is a tagging
protein, a little like the games of tag
played as a kid. It literally touches
other proteins within your cells and
adds a tag called phosphorilation and
changes their activity and function.
Well, one of its targets is called a tow
protein. Tow is a stabilizing protein.
So its function is to stabilize the
highways running across your neurons.
Again, those are brain cells. These
highways, more correctly called
microtubules, allow the cell to move
different discrete packages from one end
to the other. Think of it like dump
trucks carrying construction equipment
to other sections of the cell. These
highways remain stable and functional if
they are bound and secured by tow
proteins. Now, the issue in Alzheimer's
is that these TOAW proteins can be hyper
tagged like an annoying brat tagging
everyone over and over, although they
know that they've been tagged. We get
it, Justin. I'm it.
When Tao is hyper tagged or
hyperphosphorated by the technical term,
it scrunches up and creates tangles.
essentially it doesn't stabilize the
microtubules the highway anymore and it
forms these aggregates of proteins that
are stuck together inside the cell. So
you can imagine that if GSK3 is
hypertagging tow we begin to see
Alzheimer's issues. The main point here
is that an enzyme called GSK3
destabilizes the brain cells as well as
encourages tangles of proteins to build
up inside the brain cells. Still, that
isn't all that GSK3 is implicated in
relation to Alzheimer's because you may
have heard of beta amalloid plaques
being involved in Alzheimer's disease.
These are clumps of proteins that are
found outside of the neurons and
interfere with the neuronal
communication. Well, for those protein
clumps to get there, they have to be
secreted by brain cells. And guess what
influences their secretion?
That's right, good old GSK3.
Essentially, your cells will make more
amaloid precursor proteins, abbreviated
APS, which get released from the cell
and accumulate in these amaloid plaques.
That all happens because these enzymes
called secretases process or cut the APS
to be released out of the cell. So, the
greater activity of these particular
secretases, the worse. And it just so
happens that GSK3 doesn't act on the
secretes itself, but it will tag the
APS, the amaloid precursor proteins. And
that tag makes the environment around
the APS more attractive for the
secretases, which leads them to be more
active in processing and secretreting
the APS to form the plaques. Pretty
wild, isn't it? So we've gone over two
mechanisms by which this enzyme GSK3
encourages Alzheimer's disease. In this
last case, GSK3 makes for a friendlier
environment for amalloid beta plaque
formation. Now, how should we think
about lithium fitting into all this?
Well, it just so happens that lithium
binds and inhibits GSK3 directly among
several other ways of inhibiting this
GSK3 enzyme. And while GSK3 obviously
has multiple ways that it promotes
Alzheimer's disease, which by the way,
if you have a family history, this
enzyme is particularly active, as the
plaques produced can further stimulate
GSK3, like bratty kids egging on bratty
kids to do mischievous things. Anyway,
lithium stops GSK3. Still, there's much
more that I go over on lithium's direct
effects on GSK3, along with an
interesting interaction with magnesium,
and I go into the most effective types
of lithium in my full analysis and in
another in-depth analysis on lithium,
which is included for the Physionic
Insiders, along with all these perks
right over here. The link to join the
insiders is in the description if you're
interested. But what should we make of
all this? Regardless of these GSK3
mechanisms and how lithium could reduce
these P tow tangles and from
destabilizing the brain cells and also
stop the processing of these beta
amalloid precursor proteins that inhibit
brain cellto cell communication,
long-term potentiation and so on. I
don't think that lithium is the only one
cure to all of Alzheimer's. There's
likely other issues to address. However,
elemental lithium has been shown in
human studies to reduce and preserve
brain function in people not yet with
Alzheimer's and people developing
Alzheimer's. So, these aren't small fish
that we're talking about here. If you
want more on the human research and the
broader implications of lithium in
Alzheimer's, check it all out right
here.